"The Benefits and Side Effects of Celery"
Some plants may help us
reduce high blood pressure
and celery may be one of them.
But celery also contains relatively
high levels of sodium for a vegetable—
about 100 mg of sodium in one cup
(~130 g) of chopped celery.
Even though it's relatively
high in sodium,
it also contains other compounds
like NBP,
the compound primarily responsible
for celery's taste and aroma,
which can relax
the smooth muscles
that line blood vessels,
potentially resulting
in lower blood pressure.
And there are other
compounds in celery
that likely have
antihypertensive effects,
but those are all based
on rodent studies—
and indeed,
celery seed appears
to lower blood pressure
in hypertensive rats.
But what about humans?
You don't know until you put
celery seed to the test,
or in this case,
celery seed extract,
in a randomized, triple-blind,
placebo-controlled,
cross-over, clinical trial.
After four weeks of taking
the celery seed extract,
systolic blood pressure dropped
by at least 10 points
and diastolic blood pressure
by about 8 points.
But the whole celery seed
equivalent would be way more
than people could eat.
Is there anything a
more modest sprinkle
of celery seed a day
might help with?
Look at this:
"Treatment of women's
sexual dysfunction
using celery seed
(Apium graveolens):
A double-blind, randomized,
placebo-controlled
clinical trial."
And this study used
a culinary-friendly dose
of celery seed—
about 500 mg.
That's about ¼ tsp per capsule,
three times per day.
At the end of six weeks,
there was
a significant improvement
in the self-reported
sexual functioning
among those eating celery seeds,
with significant improvements
across multiple measures
within just three weeks.
What about celery juice?
There was a case
report of a man
who juiced a bunch
of celery every day
and had a drop
in blood pressure
and what appeared to be a
nonrandomized controlled trial
in which an undisclosed amount
of celery juice seemed to help.
A review concluded
that celery can be considered
an antihypertensive agent,
but the quality of evidence
seems slight.
What's the downside though?
Well, celery seed
is generally considered safe,
and a safety evaluation
was performed
in the blood pressure trial
that indicated so,
but maybe not for everybody.
Here is a case report
of someone who had been taking
about two tablespoons
of dried celery leaves a day,
and it seemed to cause overactive
thyroid gland activity;
the same happened
to this woman,
who had been taking celery
extract powder for weight loss.
She did lose 57 pounds (26 kg)
in 78 days
but that was likely because
the celery extract
led to hyperthyroidism.
That is not a healthy way
to lose weight,
risking side effects with names
like thyrotoxic paralysis.
Celery is also
an allergen for some,
often called
"pollen-related food allergy."
People who are allergic
to some pollens
are more likely to have
an allergy to celery,
such as what happened
in this rare case
of severe anaphylactic shock
after consumption
of raw celery.
Some only get allergic reactions
to celery
if they eat it
before exercising.
Heating celery eradicates
symptoms for about 50 percent
of people with a celery allergy,
but those who react
to raw celery also react
when it's dried.
Even if you don't have
a celery allergy,
a warning for those
who eat a lot of celery,
celery juice, or celeriac,
also known as celery root.
There are compounds
called psoralens
in the celery/parsnip/
parsley family
that can make you
sensitive to sunlight.
Farmworkers can suffer
from a condition
known as celery blisters,
when handling plants without
skin protection in the sun.
Even grocery store workers
who go from the produce aisle
to the tanning salon
can get into trouble.
These compounds can make
their way into our skin
from the inside out as well,
and they are not
destroyed by cooking.
Too much time in the sun after
commencing a "celery soup diet"
or spending time
on a tanning bed
an hour after eating
just one large celery root
may be enough to result
in a serious blistering burn.